Today's דף daf is כ"ה chaf hey and we pick up on
the very first line of כ"ה chaf hey
and the discussion here is about what types of things you salt
on the מזבח. mizbe'ach. The basic conclusion was that you salt things
that are burnt on the מזבח, mizbe'ach, not blood and not the
well there was a question about wood, whether wood is actually something
that is given as a מנחה mincha or as wood itself that's
burnt directly. Do you burn wood on wood? So if we take
out wood, what is the other thing that we would not burn,
so other than blood?
So the גמרא Gemara says let's look at the first line, pick
up from the very first word on כ"ה עמוד א': chaf hey
amud aleph: אפיק עיצי דאיילו לנסכים.
Appik eitzei d'ayalu l'nesachim.
Okay, take out wood because maybe wood according to רבי Rebbi he
treats it as a real מנחה mincha you would salt it, but
put in נסכים nesachim the wine because the wine you don't burn,
the wine that comes with a קרבן korban you pour down a
tube that's on one of the קרנות karnot of the מזבח mizbe'ach
and you don't burn it and therefore it is something that we
would not salt. דתניא, Detanya, we taught in a ברייתא: braita: אבל
היין והדם והעצים והקטורת אין טעונין מלח. Aval hayayin vehadam veha'eitzim vehaktoret
ein te'unim melach. So
here are four things: wine and blood, that we understand, that's the
idea of things that you don't burn. But now we have עצים
eitzim which again I'm back in there, we got back in there,
which work if you're not like רבי, Rebbi, you don't treat it
like a קרבן, korban, you burn it directly but not on other
wood, and קטורת. ktoret. Now קטורת ktoret is what you burn on
the מזבח הזהב. mizbe'ach hazahav. That's strange because that is something that
you burn, but you burn it on the מזבח הזהב. mizbe'ach hazahav.
So the גמרא Gemara is going to explain the logic for all
of these. Let's take a look. מני, Manni, who's this going like?
אי רבי, Ei Rebbi, if it's רבי Rebbi that says that you
salt wood and you burn it on other wood, קשיא עצים, kashya
eitzim, we don't understand what wood is doing there. אי רבנן, Ei
rabbanan, if it's the Rabbis, not the Rabbis that argue on רבי
Rebbi but the Rabbis of our משנה mishna or the Rabbis that
we have been sort of positing is this general position of the
ברייתא, braita, which is things that you burn
as opposed to you know things that you don't burn, so קשיא
קטורת, kashya ktoret, we don't understand קטורת ktoret because קטורת ktoret is
something that you burn. So the גמרא Gemara says okay הא כמאן
היא דתניא, ha k'man hi detanya, it's the following תנא tanna that
we taught in the ברייתא: braita: רבי ישמעאל בנו של רבי יוחנן
בן ברוקה אומר Rebbi Yishmael b'no shel Rebbi Yochanan ben Beroka omer
מה הפרת מפורס דבר המקבל טומאה והעולה לאישים ויתנו על המזבח החיצון.
Mah haparat meforas davar hamikabel tumah veha'oleh l'ishim veyitnu al hamizbe'ach hachitzon.
So
here are three criteria: דבר המקבל טומאה, davar hamikabel tumah, והעולה לאישים,
veha'oleh l'ishim, עולה לאישים oleh l'ishim is the one we're familiar with,
things that you burn, which would exclude the blood and the נסכים.
nesachim. So that's clear that would also exclude נסכים nesachim from things
you burn. But he has two other criteria that exclude these two
other objects. One is מקבל טומאה, mekabel tumah, it has to be
able to become טמא, tamei, and the other is is that it's
burnt on the outer מזבח. mizbe'ach. So burnt on the outer מזבח
mizbe'ach is obviously there to exclude the קטורת ktoret which is burnt
on the מזבח הזהב. mizbe'ach hazahav. So the things that are טמא
tamei is there to exclude the wood. So let's take a look
actually it fits the exact order that the ברייתא braita listed it.
Does it fit the order?
דבנא? Dabna? No no, יין yayin and דם dam are mentioned first
so it's not exactly given it old letter already before so that's
true. Okay so
anyway יצאו דם ויין שאין עולין לאישים, Yatze'u dam veyayin she'ein olin
l'ishim, so wine and the blood are excluded, they're not burnt. So
everybody, anybody who adopts the position of things that are burnt like
the חכמים chachamim that we were dealing with would also exclude the
wine, not just blood, so everybody presumably would agree with that that
it's not burnt and
therefore we would not salt the נסכים nesachim then.
So that's what the גמרא Gemara said. You're right. So the ברייתא
braita shouldn't have mentioned עצים eitzim which is debatable with whatever that
was the first line we just read today אפיק עיצי דאיילו לנסכים.
Appik eitzei d'ayalu l'nesachim. Why was it not in that original? That
I don't know, why it had to come through a change of
facts? That I don't know. There actually is though if you remember
when we dealt with נסכים, nesachim, there is an opinion that you
would actually sprinkle the wine towards the fire and let it be
burnt, although generally the גמרא Gemara assumes the position that you would
pour it down the funnel. So maybe it had to do with
that other opinion.
According to that position, then we have to
salt the נסכים nesachim then. Right. Okay, so anyway it excludes blood
and wine. יצאה קטורת שאינה על המזבח החיצון, Yatze'ah ktoret she'einah al
hamizbe'ach hachitzon,
you exclude the קטורת ktoret which is burnt you know in the
morning and in the late afternoon every day, that is not on
the outer מזבח, mizbe'ach, it's on the
מזבח הזהב. mizbe'ach hazahav. And then where was he? I skipped a
line of course. יצאו עצים Yatze'u eitzim no I skipped a line
did I? I skipped the יצאו עצים yatze'u eitzim I'm sorry okay
let's go back. Okay. יצאו עצים Yatze'u eitzim גיי פרעג gei freg
me if I make a mistake.
יצאו עצים שאין מקבלים טומאה. Yatze'u eitzim she'ein mekabelim tumah. So first
we exclude the wood that is not מקבל טומאה. mekabel tumah. I'll
get back to that in a minute.
יצאו דם ויין שאין עולים לאישים Yatze'u dam veyayin she'ein olim l'ishim
and יצאה קטורת שאינה על המזבח החיצון. veyatze'ah ktoret she'einah al hamizbe'ach
hachitzon. Now what does it mean that wood is not מקבל טומאה?
mekabel tumah? So of course logically that makes sense, only things that
are מקבל טומאה mekabel tumah are food and vessels. Wood is neither
a food nor a vessel.
make it, but it's raw material, and a raw material's not a
vessel. Right.
So that makes sense. The only problem with this is that there's
a גמרא Gemara that speaks about חיבת הקודש, chibas hakodesh, that things
that are dedicated for the מקדש Mikdash and that are going to
be somehow put on the מזבח, mizbe'ach, the חיבת הקודש, chibas hakodesh,
the lovingness as it were of the sanctuary,
raises their significance and makes them able to be מקבל טומאה. mekabel
tumah. And it actually explicitly in that list includes wood. So how
do you deal with the fact that the משנה Mishnah here says
that wood is not מקבל טומאה? mekabel tumah? So רש"י Rashi says
that's a דרבנן derabanan concept, דאורייתא de'oraisa it's not מקבל טומאה. mekabel
tumah. Okay, that solves it. תוספות Tosafos says no no no, that's
a דאורייתא de'oraisa concept. So how do we explain it? So first
תוספות Tosafos suggests maybe whether you consider wood in the חיבת הקודש
chibas hakodesh category depends on the debate of רבי Rebbi and the
חכמים Chachamim before. If you think that wood is actually a קרבן
מנחה korban mincha per se and it's offered on other wood, then
it's like a food in a way because then it acts as
being similar to the מנחה mincha that you give, you know, although
you don't afford a מנחה mincha or whatever you're choosing to give
wood, you're treating it as you know as as some type of
a a dear thing of yours and you're bringing it as a
קרבן, korban, so then it is מקבל טומאה. mekabel tumah. If you
פסק pasken like the חכמים Chachamim that if you want to give
wood you just use it as firewood and not as an offering,
then it wouldn't be חיבת הקודש. chibas hakodesh. So that fits very
nicely with that. And the other thing I think תוספות Tosafos says
in a second and the other thing תוספות Tosafos says is that
maybe all אין מקבל טומאה ein mekabel tumah means is אין מקבל
טומאה ein mekabel tumah in normal scenarios, meaning in non-מקדש Mikdash context.
Normally wood is not מקבל טומאה, mekabel tumah, even if it's מקבל
טומאה mekabel tumah here since normally it's not therefore it's excluded.
Yes, go with the idea of what you consider the קרבן korban
or the wood according to רבי Rebbi as food for the מזבח.
mizbe'ach. Right, so it becomes like food.
Oh, that's a good point. Did the רבי Rebbi use the phrase
food for the מזבח? mizbe'ach?
Well we always used the idea.
Right, right. So once you bring it as a קרבן, korban, a
קרבן korban then is framed as food, right, that's a very nice
way.
Okay, yeah, but the point from is in a friend out is
that wood wood is able to be become something to be מקבל
mekabel but what it's fashioned when it's finished into a grater or
something else so that naming this as a קרבן, korban, naming this
as something that I'm going to bring is the finishing stroke right
that determined this is the end product.
Alright, but that's a nice point and but again an end product
is not normally sufficient if your end product is not a כלי,
kli, but I hear the point. It doesn't objectively serve as a
כלי, kli, but it's a nice point and it and it reinforces
תוספות Tosafos point. Okay, so that's how we have these set of
things that's not just about burnt but it's also about things that
are on the outer מזבח mizbe'ach and excluding wood that's not מקבל
טומאה. mekabel tumah. We continue now with
אלא טעמא ela ta'ama one two three we're about ten lines down
first word in the line, כה עמוד א kaf-hei amud aleph אלא
טעמא דמיעטיה קרא לדם. ela ta'ama d'mi'atei kra l'dam. So the reason
we know that blood is excluded that you don't salt it is
because the פסוק pasuk excluded it, because it says מנחתך. minchascha.
What?
מנחתך ולא
דמך
minchascha
velo
damecha and that we've learned a principle that it has to be
things that are burnt. הלא הכי Halo hachi were it not excluded
by the פסוק, pasuk, הוה אמינא דם ליבעי מלח, hava amina dam
liv'ei melach, I would have said salt the blood. Now we have
a problem though. כיון דמלחה נפיק ליה מתורת דם, kivan de-malcheh nafik
lei mi-toras dam, as
once you salt it, it stops being considered blood and you cannot
use it for כפרה. kaparah. Why is that true? דאמר זעירי אמר
רבי חנינא, de-amar Ze'iri amar Rabbi Chanina, for זעירי Ze'iri says in
the name of רבי חנינא, Rabbi Chanina, דם שבישלו אינו עובר עליו.
dam she-bishlo eino over alav. If you cooked blood and you ate
it, you do not transgress you don't get כרת, kares, maybe there's
a לאו, lav, maybe you get nothing, maybe only דרבנן, derabanan, you
don't
and you don't transgress the prohibition of blood if you eat cooked
blood. I'll get back to this in a minute. And אמר ואמר
רב יהודה דידיה אמר, amar ve-amar Rav Yehuda didei amar, and רב
יהודה Rav Yehuda in his own name said, not in the name
of זעירי, Ze'iri, but maybe he took this logic one step further
and he said, I'm sorry no it could be and רב יהודה
אמר זעירי, Rav Yehuda amar Ze'iri, and רב יהודה Rav Yehuda said
in the name of זעירי, Ze'iri, דם שמלחו אינו עובר עליו. dam
she-malcho eino over alav. Not only if you cooked it but even
if you just salted it. Presumably this is on a print, not
cooked it, presumably this is based on a principle in the גמרא
Gemara in חולין Chullin which we use by כשרות kashrus issues which
is מליח הרי הוא כרותח, maliach harei hu ke-rosei'ach,
salting is like is like roasting. That now some say that that's
also the principle we use why salt extracts blood, that you know
if you roast something on an open fire on a spit you
know so it doesn't cook the blood back in its blood the
blood just falls away, the heat draws out the blood. Salting also
is the way you כשר kasher something, the salt draws out the
blood. Now it doesn't, it's not by the principle of heat it's
by the principle of osmosis or whatever but some say that that's
also the גמרא's Gemara logic is this idea that salt is like
heat. The גמרא Gemara specifically uses the logic salt is like heat
when it comes to transfer of taste, that if you have something
very salty and it touches something else we assume that the same
way heat draws out the taste from one to the other, the
salt draws it out and you have to worry you know about
בשר בחלב basar be-chalav and those types of issues if you have
or טרפות treifus if you have a טרפה treifa salty thing around.
That's מליח כרותח. maliach kerosei'ach. Here this... What it seems like the
גמרא gemara is doing is also saying this idea of בישול bishul
is if you cook something that's defined not as real blood and
you are חייב. chayav. If you salt something, it's also not real
blood and you're not חייב. chayav. I want to omit this statement
and then go back to it. Just hold on. רב יהודה Rav
Yehuda דידיה didei אמר, amar, רב יהודה Rav Yehuda says in his
own name, not in the name of זעירי, Ze'iri, it's really a
different point. But איברים שטלאן והעלן
אין בהם משום ריח ניחוח. eivarim shetol'on v'he'elon ein bahem mishum rayach
nichoach. If you first charred or roasted the limbs of an עולה
olah let's say, and then you put it on the מזבח, mizbe'ach,
you're not יוצא yotzei the obligation. The קרבן's korban kosher because of
the blood, but you're not יוצא yotzei the obligation of that it
should be לריח ניחוח, l'rayach nichoach, a pleasing scent, because once they've
been, the pleasing scent comes as soon as when you put them
first on the fire. Once they've been pre-charred,
pre-roasted, it's not going to smell so good, so you're not יוצא
yotzei the פסוק pasuk of לריח ניחוח. l'rayach nichoach. Anyway, let's answer
the גמרא's gemara question and then we can discuss this thing of
blood. To how could I have thought that you salt blood if
we're assuming that if you salted blood you're not חייב chayav for
eating blood, you also can't use it for כפרה?
kapparah? Now, we're going to say that they are two different paths.
Well, the reason is, what does the תורה torah say when it
says כל נפש מכם לא תאכל דם ואני נתתיו לכם על המזבח
לכפר על נפשותיכם לפני השם kol nefesh mikem lo tochal dam v'ani
netativ lachem al hamizbe'ach lechaper al nafshoteichem lifnei Hashem and therefore כל
נפש מכם לא תאכל דם? kol nefesh mikem lo tochal dam? So
there's an assumption that there's a couple of assumptions that always are
linking the two. Number one, if you remember, what type of blood
do you use for זריקת הדם? zerikas hadam? It only is דם
כנפש נשמה יוצא בה, dam kanefesh neshama yotzei bah, the blood that
is when the animal dies, that's the life force, the life spurt.
That's also the only blood that you're חייב כרת chayav kares on.
Other blood you get a לאו, lav, but you can't use for
זריקת הדם. zerikas hadam. Here,
in the
reverse, if this is blood that we're not חייב chayav for eating,
then it's also blood that you can't use for זריקת הדם. zerikas
hadam. There's an assumption that those two are very tightly linked and
it's the same blood that works for one works for the other.
Or you can always put the blood and put the salt on
after.
But no, the whole point is that you salt something that you're
about to put on the מזבח.
mizbe'ach. Maybe it meant it was salted and he resalted. It didn't
say when he salt.
That's interesting. Let's see the גמרא gemara gives some similar type of
answer. And that's our question: if you're not חייב chayav for it,
you can't use it for כפרה. kapparah. So the גמרא's gemara answer
is מה דתימא mah d'teima I might have thought משתבא
במשהו למצוה דעלמא, mishtaba b'mashehu l'mitzvah d'alma, just a tiny little salt,
not enough to make it considered like בישול, bishul, not enough to
make you exempt from the חיוב chiyuv of blood, like a little
tiny bit of salt to do the מצוה mitzvah of salting, and
therefore it would still be considered blood, קא משמע לן kama shma
lan that even that you don't do because it is not something
that is burnt. So we're now going to turn to this question
about דם שבישלו. dam shebishlo. Let me say two things about that
and then we'll see more in the גמרא. gemara. One is that
this is really like one place the גמרא gemara says this. תוספות
Tosfos seizes this idea and for תוספות Tosfos this becomes a huge
idea
להלכה l'halacha because anytime you forget to salt your meat—this is not
when you go to the supermarket
and everything is
salted—you buy a piece of meat from the butcher in the time
of תוספות Tosfos and you salt it at home, and a lot
of us know that our mothers or grandmothers or whatever knew how
to salt meat, which is like a dying skill now anyway. By
the way, if you buy Morton's kosher salt and you look at
the side, it tells you instructions for koshering your meat. I am
serious. It actually pretty much is correct. What?
Regular salt or
kosher salt? On the kosher salt.
The reason it's called kosher salt is it was koshering salt because
the flakes were large and anyway, back to this point.
For תוספות Tosfos this is a huge issue because let's say you
would always have these questions of I forgot to salt the piece
of meat and I cooked it in the pot. Okay, so תוספות
Tosfos say that it's always going to be only an איסור דרבנן.
issur d'rabbanan. Now, this just says אין עובר עליו. ein over alav.
אין עובר עליו ein over alav by blood could mean you don't
get כרת, kares, but it could still be an איסור דאורייתא. issur
d'oraissa. The גמרא gemara very much recognizes two levels of blood: blood
that you get כרת kares and blood that's just a לאו. lav.
תוספות Tosfos takes this גמרא gemara as להלכה, l'halacha, we'll discuss it
in a minute, רש"י Rashi and whatever, and תוספות Tosfos says that
אין עובר עליו ein over alav being it's only דרבנן. d'rabbanan. So
therefore whenever you have a case of somebody who forgot to salt
their meat and wound up cooking it, which is you don't know
because if you haven't cooked it yet, go salt it, for תוספות
Tosfos it's always just an איסור דרבנן issur d'rabbanan and that allows
for certain leniencies.
Whatever the pot you cooked it in, is there a problem with
that?
There are other times we apply those things by איסורי דרבנן, issurei
d'rabbanan, but in certain cases of ספק safek and other types of
things, תוספות Tosfos for every scenario is in דרבנן. d'rabbanan. The רמב"ם
Rambam never ruled this way about דם שבישלו dam shebishlo and we'll
see later about רש"י. Rashi. So
it's a real question whether we פסקן pasken it with real נפקא
מינה nafka mina in like חולין Chullin in context cases. The other
issue here is why are you not עובר over on it? We
haven't explained that. The point is that you cooked it. If I
take נבילה neveilah and I cook it, it's still נבילה, neveilah, so
presumably the reason is And it's similar to this idea of דם
שהנשמה יוצאת בו, dam shehaneshama yotzeis bo, which it has to be
in its natural state. And when it's not in its natural state,
it's not considered that like lifeblood and therefore, you know, you're not
חייב, chayav, you don't use it for זריקה. zerika. Of course, I
could think that you should still get a לאו, lav, it should
still be אסור דאורייתא, assur d'Oraisa, not כרת kares and not used
for קרבנות. korbanot. So it is interesting that תוספות Tosafot takes it
to the point where it is where you actually are it's only
דרבנן. d'Rabbanan. But again, you know, normal food that are אסור, assur,
you're certainly חייב chayav if you cook them as well. But here,
it seems like it's because it's the נפש nefesh and it's what
you use על המזבח al hamizbe'ach לכפר, lechapper, there's a sense that
it's its natural state. And once it's transformed, whether cooking or salting,
you are no longer חייב chayav on it. Yes, no longer חייב
chayav on the...
חייב chayav on the אכילה achila and therefore you also can't use
it for the מזבח. mizbe'ach.
Okay, but you weren't חייב chayav for the בישול.
bishul. Right, right, right. No, there's only an איסור בישול issur bishul
by בשר בחלב. basar bechalav. An interesting thing to think in comparison
is the יין מבושל yayin mevushal that you can't use יין מבושל
yayin mevushal for the מזבח, mizbe'ach, right? I mean, also the non-Jews
also didn't use it, but since it was not something that was
offered על המזבח, al hamizbe'ach, that's also why it... it's excluded from
a lot of those laws of סתם יינם stam yeinam because it
was not relevant to that world of worship. So again, once things
are not in their natural state, you know, that excludes them. Of
course, except for what a whole מסכת masechet is about which is
מנחה, mincha, which is something you do bake. But oh, for you
know, those types of things which are which are given fundamentally in
that natural state, the wine, the blood, etc., בישול bishul kicks them
out of that category.
So here's my question to you on this then, because
is
it its most natural state or the מזבח? mizbe'ach? And and I'll
say what I mean by that or draw it out for a...
yeah, I have a question, because you've נותר. nosar. You can't use
it on a מזבח, mizbe'ach, but it is in its natural state.
So like let's say I drink... let me say I drink the
blood a day later, right? So I couldn't have used it on
מזבח, mizbe'ach, but I didn't do anything to it. So am I
עובר over on anything?
Yeah, that we never say. We never say that blood, you mean
you mean blood that I slaughtered in my in an animal I
slaughtered in my backyard, not a קרבן. korban. Yeah, no, we never
say that that it has to... this particular blood has to be
ראוי למזבח, ra'ui lamizbe'ach, meaning I could also say it's not it's
not from a קרבן, korban, it's not ראוי למזבח. ra'ui lamizbe'ach. We
just say in physical state it has to be the same type
of blood you would put על המזבח. al hamizbe'ach. Okay, so נותר
nosar is the same physical state. The reason blood is... like us...
congealing, we'll get to it in a minute. So let's take a
look now at the גמרא Gemara about congealing. Okay, that's exactly what
the next גמרא Gemara is about. Okay, so that's the גמרא. Gemara.
Yes, I may have salted it a little bit, but you are
right, if you heavily salt it, it's like cooking it. You're not
חייב chayav and you do not... you cannot use it for זריקה
zerika דם. dam. גופא. Gufa. Now let's go back and look at
this statement.
אמר זעירי אמר רבי חנינא: Amar Ze'iri amar Rabbi Chanina: דם שבישלו,
dam shebishlo, if you cook blood, אינו עובר לאו, eino over lav,
you're not חייב. chayav.
יתיב רבא Yativ Rava and Rava was sitting וקאמר לה להא שמעתא.
veka'amar lah lehah shma'ata. He was saying over this teaching. איתיביה אביי:
Eisivei Abaye: so Abaye asked Rava. הקפה את הדם, hikfeh et hadam,
here you go, that's what Mike was saying, if you basically froze
the blood, or you know, got congealed, it's hard now, ואכלו, ve'achalo,
and you ate it. So what happens if you eat blood, you
don't drink it? Or, או שהמחהו את החלב וגמאו, o shehimchehu et
hachelev u'gma'o, you took forbidden fat and you dissolved... not dissolved it,
you liquified it, and then you drank it. So you drank something
that you normally eat, eat something you normally drink. Is it considered
enough כדרכו, kedarko, the normal way of eating it, and a normal
state of the object that you would be חייב? chayav? So the
ברייתא braisa says what?
חייב, chayav, you are חייב. chayav. So what do you see? Here
you went ahead and you transformed the blood, and it's assuming that
קפאו kefao is essentially the same as בישלו, bishlo, and nevertheless you
are חייב. chayav. So let's see what the גמרא Gemara's answer is.
So the גמרא Gemara says לא קשיא: lo kashya: כאן שהקפה באור
כאן שהקפה בחמה. kan shehikfeh be'ur, kan shehikfeh bechama. So it's not
even where he הקפה, hikfeh, which means like קפוא, kafu, like what
you would say nowadays, right, which is frozen, it's treating הקפה hikfeh
as some type of hardening it through congealing it. And it says
and this is why the גמרא Gemara is assuming that it was
the same as בישול, bishul, it's assuming you use heat to basically
get it to be congealed. And it says oh, it depends what
type of heat you use. Did you use fire or did you
do it in the sun? Now why should that matter?
We say if you use fire then
it's מבושל mevushal and you're not חייב. chayav. If you use the
sun then it is ראוי למזבח. ra'ui lamizbe'ach. Now why is... and
you are חייב. chayav. Now why is the sun ראוי למזבח? ra'ui
lamizbe'ach? What difference does it make? Now normally the difference we make
between fire and heat from fire and heat from sun is more
when we care about the process, not the end result. Like for
שבת Shabbos for example, we say you're חייב chayav if you do
cooking by fire, not if you basically cook something with the sun
or use you know... why? Because fire is the normal way, it's
דרכו, darko, and sun is not the normal way. And that's where
we have to make you חייב chayav for doing a particular type
of an act. This act has to be the classic act. The
classic act of cooking uses fire, doesn't use the sun. But here
presumably we're saying the object is not in its natural state. So
what difference does it make? Now maybe you could still make a
difference. You could say fire is basically a man-made type of a
process and therefore it's seen as a changed state where sun is
not seen as a changed state. The הגמרא Gemorah though assumes that
that's not the difference. The הגמרא Gemorah assumes at least how רש״י
Rashi explains and it sits with the הגמרא Gemorah assumes that the
difference is that when it's done by the heat it's irreversible. When
it's done by fire it's irreversible. When it's done by sun it
can actually restore its prior state which probably fits with the idea
if it was all natural then it can naturally restore itself as
well. If it's something that is more not constructible but what word
is it not unnatural but anyway manufactured you know somehow a product
of human culture then it is something that after that you know
will not go back to its natural state.
Yeah so my question on that then is that an issue of
prophecy again or is it an issue of מציאות? metzius? That because
on שבת Shabbos then you perhaps that dichotomy between חמין chamin אצל...
etzel... חמין chamin מים mayim you know it's going to restore itself
and then you couldn't even... right.
So it sounds like the הגמרא Gemorah is focusing on the מציאות
metzius here as part of the ability to restore itself or not.
Okay but it might be inferring a certain מציאות metzius based on
whether it's a natural or manufactured process.
Okay so the guess would be or the test case would be
if I had something else is דם dam more restorable
like you know even by fire whatever it would be? Exactly, exactly.
So let's take a look at the הגמרא. Gemorah. Okay so the
הגמרא Gemorah is saying it matters whether it was done by fire
or by the sun.
So that's another בסיס basis essentially. So there's nothing new with that.
Well it's saying that even though the sun is the reason of
בישול bishul is not because there was an act of בישול bishul
because why would you know you need a פסוק pasuk to say
that. So if the logic... and they never had a פסוק pasuk
there. So if the logic of בישול bishul was its not natural
state then you understand why maybe it didn't initially distinguish but now
it's telling no no we can distinguish between whether it was with
the sun or whether whatever whether we're going to call it natural
or whether it's reversible or so on. So let's take a look.
So הגמרא Gemorah is saying yes you're חייב chayav but that one
was with the sun. So why is that? לא קשיא כאן בשפיר
באור כאן בשפיר בחמה באור לא הדר בחמה הדר. lo kashya kan
beshapir be'ur kan beshapir bechamah be'ur lo hadar bechamah hadar.
In the fire it will not revert to its natural state. With
the sun it will revert. So the הגמרא Gemorah says באור נמי
לימא be'ur nami leima so even if it's true that it will
revert in the sun why are you חייב chayav when you eat
it? Let us say הואיל ואידחי אידחי ho'il ve'idchi idchi
since it was pushed off למזבח lemizbeach now in its current state
it can't be used then it remains pushed off. Right this is
the principle of דחוי. dichuy. And here Michael this is more relevant
to your types of questions of נותר nosar because here we're basically
saying that since were this a קרבן korban once it hit this
state of being you know shriveled or congealed it would not be
acceptable even if it became fit again because of the principle of
דחוי dichuy it was pushed off. So when it comes to you
eating the דם dam right let us also say that you should
not be חייב chayav because this will never be דם dam that
will become acceptable again on the מזבח. mizbeach. Yeah the איסור issur
of דם dam by קרבנות korbanos had to prevent it...
presumably the reason why it prevented it
if it did then you have a...
right right. So הגמרא Gemorah says so why don't we say that?
Or why don't we say basically at least if you ate it
while it was congealed maybe another way to make it not so
much sort of the הלכות halachos of קרבנות korbanos if you ate
it while it was congealed that's a state that it never could
have worked for the מזבח mizbeach so why are you חייב? chayav?
So הגמרא Gemorah says דהא בעא מיניה רבי מרבי מני מרבי יוחנן.
deha ba'a minei Rebbi merabi Mani merabi Yochanan. Rabi Mani asked of
Rabi Yochanan. דם שקרש ואכלו מהו. dam shekarash ve'achalo mahu.
If you have blood that basically congealed and you ate it are
you חייב chayav or not? In its currently congealed state which seems
to have been the exact earlier statement about הקפה את הדם ואכלו.
hikpah es hadam ve'achalo. So let's see what the answer is. אמר
ליה הואיל ונדחה ידחה. amar lei ho'il venidchah yidacheh. Since it was
pushed off it remains pushed off. Which means that since it now
cannot be used for the מזבח mizbeach therefore you are not חייב.
chayav. Okay so okay that's very nice but it sort of contradicted
the previous line about דם שהקפהו. dam shehikpahu. But anyway now the
הגמרא Gemorah is saying look you know once you're working within this
principle of change state no matter how it got to this change
state whether it is fire or sun you should... it should not
sit for the מזבח mizbeach at least currently in this change state
and therefore you should be פטור patur and that's what ר' יוחנן
Rebbi Yochanan responded
for רבי מני. Rebbi Mani. רבי מני. Rebbi Mani. I'm sorry. So
how do you deal with the ברייתא braisa that says that you're
חייב? chayav? Okay once we have this whole idea of natural state.
So let's see what the הגמרא Gemorah says. אישתיק. ishtik.
He was silenced. ורהטיה דאביי קא רמי. ve'rahatya de'Abaye ka rami. אמר
ליה amar lei so then Abaye himself suggested an answer. דילמא... dilma...
some take out the word ודאי. vadai. דילמא כאן בחצות החיצוניות כאן
בחצות הפנימיות. dilma kan bachatzos hachitzoniyos kan bachatzos hapnimiyos.
Maybe there's a difference between an inner and an outer חצות. chatzos.
What does this mean? Let's take a look. Now we'll go back
and figure it out. אמר אדכרתן מילתא. amar adkartan milta.
You reminded me of a thing, דאמר רב חסדא, d'amar Rav Chisda,
because Rav Chisda says דם שקרש, dam shekarash, if you have blood
that congealed, בחטאות, bechataos,
with the חטאות, chataos, meaning the outer חטאות, chataos, if you see
in the side of the page is the גרסא girsa חטאות החיצוניות,
chataos hachitzoniyos, the outer חטאות, chataos, ואכלו חייב, veachalo chayav, you're חייב.
chayav. Why? ולקח ונתן אמר רחמנא, velakach venasan amar Rachmana, and this
is a בר לקיחה ונתינה הוא. bar lekicha unetina hu. What do
you have to do with an outer חטאת? chatas? You have to
take the blood and put it on the מזבח. mizbeach. Even congealed
blood you can smear on the מזבח. mizbeach. You take a little
piece of the congealed blood and you smear it on. Okay, that's
possible. But בחטאות פנימיות, bechataos pnimiyos, in the inner חטאות, chataos, or
wait,
did I skip a line? Yeah, ובחטאות פנימיות ואכלו פטור. uvechataos pnimiyos
veachalo patur. If you did it in an inner חטאת, chatas, you're
פטור. patur. וטבל והזה אמר רחמנא. vetaval vehizah amar Rachmana. You have
to dip your finger and sprinkle, והאי לאו בר טבילה והזאה הוא.
vehai lav bar tevila vehazaah hu. With congealed you can't dip. Dip
means it's a liquid, and you can't sprinkle, you only sprinkle a
liquid. If it's solid you throw it. Okay, you can take and
place congealed blood, but you cannot dip and sprinkle congealed blood. Now
so what did we just say? So we said that you're חייב
chayav on the outer חטאת, chatas, you're פטור patur on the inner,
no, yeah, you're פטור patur on the inner חטאת chatas
if you eat it. Okay, so now we're saying okay that's all
very nice for outer and inner חטאת, chatas, but what about normal
blood that I've got, you know, not a חטאת? chatas? Am I
חייב chayav or am I פטור patur if it is אם הוא
קרש? im hu karash? So the way that רש"י Rashi explains this
is the following: He says we have not given up our distinction
about fire versus sun. Anything and תוספות Tosafot says this as well,
but although תוספות Tosafot had a different גרסא girsa in רש"י, Rashi,
so he thinks he's arguing on רש"י, Rashi, but our רש"י Rashi
says and תוספות Tosafot agree and says like this: Anything done by
heat is a real transformation, and therefore you are פטור patur when
you cook דם dam anywhere, whether it's an inner חטאת, chatas, outer
חטאת, chatas, דם dam from your butcher in the backyard, heat of
a fire transforms it, it's different blood, it's פטור. patur. It's an
eating result.
And the same thing for salt.
Sun is natural, maybe reversible, I would even emphasize natural. It does
not make the blood considered to be, you know, like transformed. It
just creates a practical problem. Right now you can't do זריקה. zarika.
So therefore, if it were my own blood in my backyard, I'd
still be חייב chayav because it's not really transformed and therefore it's
still דם dam that I'm eating. If it however is of a
קרבן, korban, and then it specifically moves into the status of not
being able to be used, which is true by the outer חטאת,
chatas. no, it's true by the inner חטאת, chatas not by the
outer חטאת. chatas Only by the inner חטאת chatas. where practically it
can't be used, even though it hasn't transformed, would I be פטור?
patur? And that's the case that הגמרא haGemara is distinguishing. They're distinguishing
between inner and outer חטאת chatas is blood that solidified because of
the sun. Is that clear? To repeat it again, meaning דם שבשלו,
dam shebishlo, right, it's a very bizarre גמרא. Gemara. It says oh,
it depends if you're eating from the outer or inner קרבן. korban.
But I want to know what happened if I סתם stam eat
blood. So the way רש"י Rashi and תוספות, Tosafot, at least again
our רש"י Rashi and תוספות Tosafot explain this case is, cooked is
complete with fire or with salt is complete transformation, you're פטור. patur.
Totally different type of a thing. If it's just congealed naturally or
congealed by the sun, then that's no longer a question of transformation.
That's not transformed. That's just practically right now it can't be used,
it's not in a state that can be sprinkled. Does that get
me off the hook? הגמרא haGemara says that only gets you off
the hook if it is the blood of an inner חטאת. chatas,
That's the only type of thing you've practically prevented is the blood
of an inner חטאת Chatas, because you can't dip and sprinkle. So
for an inner חטאת, Chatas you can't use hardened blood on המזבח
hamizbeach and you wouldn't be חייב chayav if you ate that blood.
But for everything else, it's considered in its natural state and therefore
you would be חייב.
chayav. I presume it's still פטור אבל אסור patur aval assur still
even on the inner? Yeah, we're not going to... okay. Go ahead.
I'm
sorry,
I'm sitting here the whole time very upset because I remember my
mother koshering meat. It was a very big deal, right? And they
had to keep it on a board and salt, right? Salt for
an hour. It was... no one had any idea that it's not
דאורייתא d'Oraisa if all the blood doesn't come out and if you
cook it it's okay.
No, nobody had that... it's okay, it's still דרבנן. d'Rabanan.
But the main דאורייתא, d'Oraisa, I know, well that's the
point.
You
hope, well that's the point.
You read through all...
well I want to tell you
and that's why and that's why I hope
it's even דרבנן, d'Rabanan, but I do understand your point, I totally
get it. You know, and you will have people even till today
that will buy not שחיטת shchitat not
slaughtered kosher but they'll... So the point is that yes, this גמרא
Gemara would lead to saying that any case you really don't salt
your blood, but if once you cook the meat, it's all only
איסור דרבנן. issur d'rabbanan. The only time you'd be חייב דאורייתא chayav
d'oraisa is if you ate raw meat, uncooked, right? Or you squoze,
squeezed out the blood and you drank the blood. Okay, so that's
why, you know, that if you תוספות Tosafot consistently brings this up
and consistently lowers the problem, but if you, you know, if you
read
הלכות דם hilchos dam in the שולחן ערוך Shulchan Aruch and you
read the רמב"ם, Rambam, this gets like, you know, they almost completely
bracket this סוגיא. sugya. And maybe they think it's לא להלכה, lo
l'halakha, maybe because of all these other things, you know, maybe they
feel that this is only according to the מאירי, Meiri, maybe it's
לא להלכה, lo l'halakha, or maybe they feel it's a דאורייתא d'oraisa
but not איסור כרת, issur kares, which also fits with the סוגיא,
sugya, you know, חייב chayav can sometimes be חייב כרת. chayav kares.
But you're right, meaning if you take this גמרא Gemara seriously, you
basically feel that nobody is עובר over on דאורייתא d'oraisa blood. Right.
And and so all the work that the women of these generations
did, hours and hours. Salt it to make.
But isn't that supposed to be a beautiful thing? Look how much
even איסור דרבנן issur d'rabbanan was חשוב בעיניהם chashuv beineihem that they...
Yeah. I hear your point. The גרסא girsa of רש"י Rashi that
תוספות Tosafot had, not our גרסא, girsa, says that the only thing
you're exempt for, even if you literally cook it, is from the
חטאת הפנימית. Chatas Hapnimis. Only the inner חטאת, Chatas. that gets it
out of the category of blood, it can't be for sprinkling, but
everything else, an outer חטאת Chatas, and any blood you encounter, you
know, from the butcher, that is not related, you know, that you're
still חייב chayav for. So that reading of רש"י Rashi of this
סוגיא sugya limits the entire, the whole היתר heter of cooking blood,
right, to the one case of the inner חטאת. Chatas So that's
another way you cannot feel compelled by this גמרא Gemara to turn
everything into a
דרבנן.
d'rabbanan. Let me think about
that for a second.
Wait, so then even, even if it congealed for the inner חטאת,
Chatas
even once it
decongealed,
whatever that is, you know, and you ate it, then you'd still
be exempt, like, because it was already דחוי? dachui? Or
is that only one more time? Even if it congealed... No, even
if it decongealed, whatever that is, you know,
for the inner חטאת chatas it's no longer useful, it's דחוי, dachui,
then you
wouldn't be עובר over on that either.
Right. But that's just the inner חטאת chatas, according to our רש"י
Rashi and תוספות, Tosafot, that's only when it was by the sun.
By the heat of a fire, then that would totally get out
of this...
The whole thing would have to be intentional also, like let's say,
you know, like a wave went over it, you know, these גמרא'ס
Gemara's cases, like, you know...
like as long as it's a physical
reality...
I don't have to salt it, it needs to have get salted
on it. Right, like you know, if it fell in the ocean
or something, or some, you know, is that considered salting?
One minute,
let me read let me read you the רמב"ם, Rambam, let me
read you the רמב"ם, Rambam, okay? Everybody, let me read the
רמב"ם. Rambam. ואם בישל הלב ולא קרעו אחר שבישלו. v'im bishel halev
v'lo k'rao achar shebishelo. So you cooked the heart and you forgot
to open
it, right? And and you know and then now you have all
the blood in the heart. So he says, ואם לא קרעו ואכלו
אינו חייב עליו כרת. v'im lo k'rao v'achalo eino chayav alav kares.
If you didn't tear it open to get the blood out, this
heart that you cooked, so you're not חייב כרת. chayav kares. Why?
Now first you could say, okay, the רמב"ם Rambam says you're not
עובר, over, but maybe you don't get כרת, kares, but it's still
דאורייתא. d'oraisa. But then he goes on: במה דברים אמורים בלב העוף
שאין בו כזית דם. bameh devarim amurim b'lev ha'of she'ein bo kezayis
dam. That's only by a bird heart that there's not even a
כזית kezayis of blood in the heart of a bird. אבל אם
היה לב בהמה, aval im haya lev beheima, if this was an
animal heart that you cooked and you ate it without what, not
an animal, a mammal's heart, right, that you cooked and you did
not remove the blood,
חייב כרת שהרי יש בו כזית מדם שבתוך הלב שחייבים עליו כרת.
chayav kares sheharei yesh bo kezayis midam shebetoch halev shechayavim alav kares.
So here the רמב"ם Rambam says cooked blood, and as long as
it's a כזית, kezayis, you're חייב כרת. chayav kares. So he basically
completely ignored
this
גמרא Gemara of...
of ever today that they tell you
you have to make
sure for the for
the look, this even to cook
it right, again, a דרבנן d'rabbanan is still a דרבנן. d'rabbanan. But
I'll tell you a case what comes up, okay, happened to me
actually just like a month ago. You buy a chicken and you,
you know, whatever, you throw it in the oven, right? And then
as you take it out, you realize, oh my god, they put
the giblets in this bag, right, that were not salted, right? The
liver and so on, and still there. And now you have to
throw out the whole chicken. Or do you say, well, you know,
can you assume that because of the bag, maybe it prevented transfer,
maybe there was שישים? shishim? How lenient are you going to be?
How strict are you going to be? So if you think דם
שבישלו dam shebishelo is only דרבנן, d'rabbanan, it gives you more latitude.
At the end of the day, of course I threw out the
chicken anyway, but that's me. It's asking differently to other people. But
anyway,
but I think that, you know, but you're right.
Our entire experience of blood assumes that we're dealing with a real
איסור דאורייתא issur d'oraisa and חיוב כרת chiyuv kares and not that
everything is going to wind up being a דרבנן. d'rabbanan. Okay, so
let's continue.
Alright, so for your introduction that Tosafos gives you games all the
time and things like that, how much of his approach do you
think is agenda driven? I have no idea.
But I think what Tosafos is saying is a simple application of
this גמרא, Gemara, although I will say even with this גמרא, Gemara,
you could say not כרת kares but still דאורייתא. d'oraisa. Okay, so
let's keep on going.
Okay, yeah, we are falling a little behind, but it's okay. The
גמרא Gemara says like this. ורבא דידיה אמר, V'Rava didey amar,
line starts with the word אמר, amar, it's about 10 lines before
the lines get wide. ורבא דידיה אמר, V'Rava didey amar, Rava says
in his own name, because that was in a discussion with אביי,
Abaye, אפילו בחטאת הפנימיות ואכלו חייב, afillu b'chatas hapnimiyos v'achalo chayav,
even in an inner חטאת chatas, you're חייב, chayav, although you can't
dip your finger and do זריקה, zerika, dip and do זריקה, zerika,
הואיל וכנגדו ראוי בחטאת החיצוניות, ho'il u-k'negdo ra'uy b'chatas hachitzoniyos,
since this type of blood is something that you could use for
an outer חטאת, chatas that's enough to say it's still קרבן korban
blood and therefore you would be חייב chayav if you ate it.
You might not be יוצא yotzei the קרבן korban if you tried
to do it this way, but you're חייב chayav if you ate
it. Okay. אמר רב פפא, Amar Rav Papa, רב פפא Rav Papa
said, הלכך, hilkach, therefore, דם חמור שקרש ואכלו חייב. dam chamor she-karash
v'achalo chayav.
Let's say you have donkey blood, okay, which obviously you can't use
on the מזבח. mizbeach. And not only that, it's congealed. You're still
חייב. chayav. Why? דם חמור שקרש חייב, Dam chamor
she-karash chayav,
הואיל וכנגדו ראוי
בחטאת החיצונית,
ho'il
u-k'negdo ra'uy
b'chatas hachitzonis,
since you could use this type of blood, were it not donkey
blood, were it, you know, cow blood, and you could use it
on an outer חטאת, chatas. it's enough in the category of blood
to still be
חייב chayav and everything, blood is כרת.
kares. So here you see the גמרא Gemara sort of pushing back
and saying it's very nice that there's some examples of קרבנות korbanos
that it can't be used when it's congealed, but once we have
the example of an outer חטאת Chatat that can be used when
it's congealed, any type of blood, even non-קרבן, korban, even non-כשר kasher
and whatever, would be considered to be in that category and still
ראוי ra'uy for קרבן korban and therefore still חייב. chayav. So again,
if you read this גמרא Gemara is not limiting itself to sun-baked
blood, but it's talking about even congealed by fire, then you see
why the entire גמרא Gemara becomes moot, right, רבקה? Rivka? Because then
the entire גמרא Gemara winds up saying that you're חייב chayav on
all blood because you could use it in an outer חטאת. Chatat
The way you keep the גמרא Gemara relevant for us is saying
all this discussion is sun-baked blood, but cooked blood is a total,
totally different sort. Okay. אמר רב גידל אמר רב אירי, Amar Rav
Gidel amar Rav Iri, so רב גידל Rav Gidel now says in
the name of רב אירי, Rav Iri, דם בין לח בין יבש
חוצץ. dam bein lach bein yavesh chotzetz. Since we're talking about blood,
we'll talk about, let's say you've got a little bit blood on
your arm and you go to the מקווה, mikvah, whether it's dry
or liquidy, it still creates a חציצה chatzitza between your water and
your skin.
Same for a כהן, kohen, right, if he's doing עבודה avoda and
he's got blood.
Oh, that's true also, good point. Okay. מיתיבי, Meisivei, I'll ask you
on this, הדם והדיו והדבש והחלב. hadam v'hadio v'hadvash v'hachalav. So this
is a משנה Mishnah in מקוואות. Mikvaos. Blood and ink and honey
and milk, יבשים חוצצים, yaveshim chotzetzim, if they're dried and congealed on
your skin, they're a חציצה. chatzitza. לחים אינם חוצצים, lachim einam chotzetzim,
if they're wet, they do not perform a חציצה, chatzitza, because presumably
when they're wet, they're also water permeable and the water can get
through them and get onto your skin.
גמרא Gemara says, it
has to wash off?
Well, that's what the גמרא's Gemara answer is going to be. לא
קשיא, lo kashya, הא דסריך הא דלא סריך. ha d'sarich ha d'la
sarich. Blood even wet can be a חציצה chatzitza if it's adhesive,
you know, because blood can be sticky. So therefore, if it's- what?
Honey doesn't
just wash off either, right, unless it's like very loose honey. So
if it's not adhesive, it either washes off or allows the water
through, but if it's adhesive, then we are concerned that it creates
a חציצה. chatzitza. Okay, that gets us through the issue about דם
שבשלו דם שמלחו dam she-bishlo dam she-malcho and we can see the
profound practical implications of that. Now we go on to the מצוה
mitzvah of מליחה melicha by קרבנות. korbanos. תמלח, timlach, you shall salt.
למאי אתא, l'mai asa, what's that coming to tell us? Like it
already said קרבן מנחה במלח תמלח, korban mincha b'melach timlach, okay, so
it already said מלח, melach, what תמלח timlach mean, to mean to
salt it, using it as the verb. So לכי דתניא, lechi detanya,
what we taught in the ברייתא, braisa, במלח, b'melach, with salt, יכול
תדונהו, yachol tedunehu, maybe you will תדונהו, tedunehu, which the גמרא Gemara
will discuss in a minute, but it either means put down only
a little or put down, if you put a ton of salt
on, תלמוד לומר תמלח, talmud lomar timlach, you shall salt it, which
means the normal way people salt things, as we'll see in a
minute.
אי תמלח, ei timlach, if salted, יכול במי מלח, yachol b'mei melach,
maybe you can even use salt water because apparently that's sometimes how
people would, you know, get this food salty like כבשי טמיגא, kivshei
tamiga, right? תלמוד
לומר במלח, talmud lomar b'melach, no, salt directly. ולא תשבית מלח, v'lo
sashbis melach, so do not let the salt rest from your, from
your קרבן, korban, הבא מלח שאינה שובתת. havei melach she-eina shovesses. Bring
salt that does not rest. What does that mean? ואיזו, v'eizo, what
is this? זו מלח סדומית, zo melach Sedomis, is the salt of
Sodom. Now the גמרא Gemara mentions מלח סדומית. melach Sedomis. by מים
אחרונים Mayim achronim and everybody thinks it's like this mystical salt that
comes from סדום, Sedom, like what does גמרא Gemara mean, you know?
תוספות Tosafos says we don't have מלח סדומית Melach sedomit nowadays. No,
no, מלח סדומית Melach sedomit is סדום Sedom is right by the
Dead Sea. מלח סדומית Melach sedomit is sea salt, okay? And it's
going to be contrasted in a minute to mineral salt. Okay, so
sea salt is אינה שובתת. eina shovetet. What does אינה שובתת eina
shovetet mean?
The water is always flowing, right?
Yeah, so רש"י Rashi says that it means that it's like more
powerful than than mineral salt. But the ערוך Aruch and it's put
here on the side says no, no, because the sea works even
on שבת. Shabbos. You know, it will wash up salt, you know,
onto the shores, right, even on שבת Shabbos as opposed to mineral
salt. If you've got Jewish workers, you're not mining your minerals on
שבת. Shabbos. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says
oh no, רש"י Rashi says it means that it's available in in
all seasons as opposed to mineral salt, I guess they wouldn't mine
the mineral note in certain seasons. It just tells you that you're
supposed to use sea salt for your
קרבנות. korbanos. Because it works on שבת. Shabbos. Yeah, did they use
salt for the
קרבנות korbanos in the מדבר midbar then? Like they didn't know?
I'm going to say bought it from traders and they imported it.
That's a good point. Okay, yeah, or they took it out of
מצרים. Mitzrayim. Okay, so anyway, הבא נו שאינה שובתת. Havei no she'eina
shovetet. ואיזה? Ve'eizeh? What is this? וזו מלח סדומית Vezo melach sedomit
sea salt. ומניין שאם לא מצא מלח סדומית שמהביא מלח אסטרוקנית? Uminayin
she'im lo matza melach sedomit shemeivi melach istrokanit?
How do you know if you can't find sea salt you bring
mineral salt? Okay, that's presumably what that word means, mineral salt. תלמוד
לומר תקריב. Talmud lomar takriv. You shall offer. So even if you
can't do the exact parameter, any type of way of putting salt
works.
At least for the salt. מלח סדומית Melach sedomit you're saying is
mineral salt?
No, מלח סדומית Melach sedomit is sea salt.
Right, don't say that.
Sea salt, right? סדום, Sedom, the Dead Sea, אינה שובתת, eina shovetet,
sea salt.
אסטרוקנית Istrokkanit or whatever's mineral salt.
Oh, so they really could have just said, although they were bigger
seas, they could have just said whatever, from the ים הגדול. Yam
Hagadol. I mean, you know. Why did they specify סדום? Sedom?
Yeah, because
they became an עיר מלח, ir melach, because I think the whole
imagery of סדום Sedom is with the salt.
It's the most powerful image. And right.
Why would this אסטרוקי istroki have anything to do with this?
What about the place, the industrial salt territory?
Is אסטרוקיס? Istrokis? Okay. Why, where does the word come from? Some
Roman word or something? Okay, תוספות. Tosafos. Okay, anyway, fine. So how
do I know if you don't have sea salt you can bring
mineral salt? So here answers your question Michael about how they did
it in the מדבר. midbar. תלמוד לומר תקריב. Talmud lomar takriv. Okay,
תקריב כל שהוא, Takriv kol shehu, תקריב מכל מקום. Takriv mikol makom.
תקריב וכל קרבן מנחתך במלח תמלח ולא תשבית מלח ברית אלקיך מעל
מנחתך על כל קרבנך תקריב מלח. Takriv vechol korban minchatcha bamelach timlach
velo tashbit melach berit Elokecha meal minchatcha al kol korbancha takriv melach.
Okay, so תקריב כל שהוא, Takriv kol shehu, תקריב מכל
מקום
Takriv
mikol makom
in any respect, we'll see what that means. So כל שהוא kol
shehu means even whatever type of salt, whether mineral or sea salt.
מכל מקום Mikol makom רש"י Rashi says means even if you have
to bring it from outside ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, doesn't have to
be Israeli salt.
תקריב ואפילו בשבת. Takriv va'afilu beShabbos. And now not a leniency but
a requirement, you have to put the salt on even on שבת.
Shabbos. תקריב ואפילו בטומאה, Takriv va'afilu betumah, even if you're טמא. tamei.
Meaning if it's a קרבן ציבור korban tzibbur and you bring it
בטומאה, betumah, so the that would apply to the salt that goes
with the קרבן korban as well. Okay, now the גמרא Gemara is
going to take this ברייתא braisa apart. מאי תבנוהו? Mai tivunuhu? What
does it mean I would think you would תבנוהו? tivunuhu? What does
that word mean? So אמר רבה בר בר חנה הכי קאמר: Amar
Rabbah bar bar Chana hachi ka'amar: יכול יתבוננו כתבן בטיט. Yachol yitbonenu
ketevan batit.
Maybe you shall add as much straw as much to it as
you would put straw into plaster. You put a lot of straw
into plaster, so the word תבנוהו tivunuhu is from the word תבן.
teven. Maybe you should put tons of salt into it. So קא
משמע לן ka mashma lan no, how you normally salt things. So
אמר ליה אביי, Amar lei Abaye, אי הכי יתבוננו מיבעי ליה. ei
hachi yitbonenu miba'ei lei.
The grammar doesn't work. If the word for if we're basing it
on the word תבן teven it would say יתבוננו. yitbonenu. אלא אמר
אביי יכול יאפנו כבנין. Ela amar Abaye yachol ye'afenu kevinyan.
Maybe you make it like a structure, layer upon layer upon layer
of salt. Again, meaning maybe you do a lot. So that's the
word יתבנוהו. itvunuhu.
So אמר רבה בר עולא אמרת דלמא כבנין. Amar Rabbah bar Ulla
amart dilma kevinyan. אמר ליה רבא, Amar lei Rava, so רבא Rava
said back to him, אי הכי יבננהו מיבעי ליה. ei hachi yivnenahu
miba'ei lei.
Should have said you shall build it. I would think. אלא אמר
רבא יכול תבנוהו. Ela amar Rava yachol tivnuhu. I might think you
should תבנוהו. tivnuhu. מאי תבנוהו? Mai tivunuhu? Like a little bizarre, you
just quoted the ברייתא. braisa. מאי תבנוהו? Mai tivunuhu? אמר רב אשי
יכול יתן בו טעם כבינה. Amar Rav Ashi yachol yitein bo ta'am
kevinah.
Maybe you should go a little taste of בינה. binah. Have בינה,
binah, right, you like like wisdom, like בינה binah gives the essence
into a duller, you know, a little salt, I think that was
like a classic metaphor used in in like these aphorisms, you know.
So you have this dull meat, you put a little salt on
it, it enhances the flavor. So a little בינה, binah, you know,
takes the dull person and makes them more palatable.
So therefore, קא משמע לן. ka mashma lan. קמשמלן Kamashmalan that even
not a little bit but it needs to be a heavy, not
overly heavy but not overly small, it would have to be the
amount that things are normally salted. Now the ערוך Aruch says here,
I think they have this on the side, that even with this
בינה Bina explanation the הוה אמינא Hava Amina was a lot of
salt. Yeah.
Oh no, no, no, I'm sorry, I was telling you the ערוך,
Aruch, it's on the bottom here of the גמרא Gemara right before
the, between the גמרא Gemara and רש"י. Rashi. כולהו מלח, Koldahu melach,
even a little salt, עד כדי להבין שיש בו טעם מלח, Ad
kedei lehavin sheyesh bo ta'am melach,
you know, enough to understand maybe even a small amount of salt
that you can taste it. קמשמלן, Kamashmalan, no, no, no, the way
people salt it which is more heavy.
So there is another גמרא Gemara that says, well actually not a
גמרא, Gemara, let's keep on reading one more line, we're going to
get to a little more clarification. טעם למה תמלח, Tam lama timlach,
okay.
So כיצד הוא עושה, Keitzad hu oseh, so how much salt do
you do, how do you do it? מביא האבר ונותן עליו מלח,
Meivi ha'eiver venoten alav melach, you take the limb and you salt
one side, וחוזר והופכו, Vechozer vehofcho, you flip it on the other
side, ונותן עליו מלח, Venoten alav melach, you put salt on it,
not a tiny bit, you put an entire layer on each side,
ומעלהו Umaleihu and then you put it on the מזבח. Mizbe'ach. אמר
אביי וכן לקדירה. Amar Abaye v'chen lakdeira.
Now these two words of אביי Abaye are so critical because salting
your meat, you're salting your meat, and there's a major question what
the גרסא Girsa here is. Some say וכן לקדירה V'chen lakdeira and
others say וכן לצלי. V'chen litzli. Okay, that's a huge difference. When
you roast a piece of meat you don't really need to salt
it at all, the fire draws out all the meat, all the
blood. So there was a question, maybe there was a מנהג Minhag
to put on a little bit of salt etc. So if,
but if you're roasting it, it would mean we're not talking about
a lot of salt and that also a קרבן Korban would be
a little bit of salt. If the גרסא Girsa is וכן לקדירה,
V'chen lakdeira, then he's talking about how much salt you have to
put it on like when we salt our meat to put it
in the pot because the reason there you have to put it
on is because the blood, if any blood is left it'll come
out and go back in, right? So there you have to really
get all the blood out first and it, you have to get
that out without the use of heat. So if it's saying וכן
לקדירה, V'chen lakdeira, on the one hand it tells us that there
would be, it wouldn't be just a tiny amount on the קרבנות,
Korbanot, it would be more significant, the רישומא Rishuma needs to be
more significant to get out all the salt, but it would also
tell us in the flip that the amount of salt we put
on to כשר Kasher meat is not overly excessive because the whole
point of this ברייתא Braita was to say that the amount of
salt you put on is not tons and tons of salt, it
says you know you salt one side, you flip it, you salt
the other side. So this גמרא Gemara with those two words, the
words are וכן לקדירה V'chen lakdeira as opposed to וכן לצלי V'chen
litzli which is debated, becomes very important that they inform one another
how much salt you put on a קרבן Korban and how much
salt you put on to כשר Kasher
the meat because the גרסא Girsa both גרסאות Girsaot date back very
far
or I don't know how, I don't know, I can't tell you
more about the history of the גרסא. Girsa.
Yeah, and what would
לצלי Litzli tell you?
לצלי Litzli does not really מעיקר הדין Me'ikar hadin require salt although
you might want to, it doesn't מעיקר הדין Me'ikar hadin require salt
because the fire draws it out and the blood isn't coming back,
it very easily means you just salt it perfunctorily. So and then
it would also say that that's what you do for a קרבן.
Korban. So it wouldn't tell you too much other than קרבנות Korbanot
would be a light salt. If it's וכן לקדירה, V'chen lakdeira, then
presumably we can't be too, we can't be too light because you
have to really get out the blood just by the power of
the salt. But we would on the other hand understand that when
it comes to salting your meat for כשרות, Kashrut, it's not, it
doesn't have to be too heavy because the way the גמרא Gemara
described it was number one not heavy, not טרחא יתירא Tarcha yeseira
and it says you know you salt it, you flip it, you
salt it. So that gives us a moderate understanding, an understanding of
a moderate amount of salt both for the קדירה Kdeira and for
קרבנות. Korbanot. Who has the גרסא? Girsa? התוספות Tosafot points this out.
בספר רבינו גרשום כתוב וכן לצלי. B'sefer Rabbeinu Gershom katuv v'chen litzli.
Okay but if אביי Abaye
is saying וכן לצלי V'chen litzli but you're saying he's contradicting what
we just said a second before. He said by a קרבן Korban
מביא אבר ונותן עליו מלח חוזר והופכו, Meivi eiver venoten alav melach
chozer vehofcho, that's what you do for לצלי, Litzli, a light thing,
but for קדירה Kdeira there you need a lot more. Right, okay,
okay, I thought you said קרבן, Korban, I misunderstood you. Okay, never
mind.
Okay, okay, so anyway תנו רבנן, Tanu rabanan, now כו עמוד א,
Kaf Vav Amud Aleph, our rabbis taught: מלח
שעל גבי האבר מועלין בו שעל גבי הכבש ושבראש המזבח אין מועלין
בו.
Melach she'al
gabei ha'eiver mo'alin bo, she'al gabei hakeves v'sheberosh ha'mizbe'ach ein mo'alin bo.
Once you put the salt on the actual קרבן, Korban, then if
like the קרבן Korban and there's מעילה. Me'ilah. Before it's put on
the קרבן Korban you do not yet have מעילה. Me'ilah. It's there
to be used and so on, but it's not yet מעילה. Me'ilah.
Now
אמר רב פפא, Amar Rav Papa, didn't
they have salt on?
Yeah, ready to be used, but until it's actually put on the
קרבן Korban there's no מעילה. Me'ilah. מאי קרא, Mai kraya, where do
you get this from the פסוק? Pasuk? הקרבתם לפני ה' והשליכו הכהנים
עליהם מלח, Hikravtem lifnei Hashem ve'hishlichu hakohanim aleihem melach, you shall bring
them before God and the כהנים Kohanim will put on it on
them salt, והעלו אותם עולה לה', Vehe'alu otam olah laHashem, and bring
them as an offering. So it understands that once it says והעלו
Vehe'alu in the plural after mentioning the salt, that the salt itself
is considered like a קרבן. Korban. So once the salt
is
put
We're about to say that. Okay. מן התם, min hatam, we taught
over there in שקלים. Shekalim. על המלח ועל העצים שהיו הכהנים נאותים
בהם, al hamelach v'al ha-eitzim she-hayu hakohanim ne'eisim bahem,
one of the things that בית דין Beis Din stipulated was that
wood and the salt that were in the מקדש, Mikdash, כהנים Kohanim
would have a right to use them. They would not be fully
sanctified in the sense that, you know, if a כהן Kohen used
it, you'd get מעילה. Me'ilah. You'd love it that a כהן Kohen
benefited from it, which means, you know, if a כהן Kohen is
up at the top of the מזבח Mizbeiach and it's a cold
day and he's putting on a קרבן Korban and he's got a
nice fire going there, you know, you don't have to be concerned
about מעילה Me'ilah to like be warming himself by the fire. So
the גמרא Gemara is now going to talk about the issue of
salt. Let's take a look.
Where are they going to use the salt that they've been given
permission to use? אמר
שמואל, Amar Shmuel, לא שנו אלא לקרבנן. lo shanu ela l'korbanan. When
is it that they have a right to use the salt? For
their קרבן. Korban. They bring their קרבן, Korban, they put salt on
it, and they use... and they put it on the מזבח. Mizbeiach.
But to eat it, אכל לא. achal lo.
So but not for eating. You know, when they're eating the meat
of their קרבן Korban and they say, "Ooh, this... I need a
little salt on this meat," they can't go to the salt room
and use the salt. That salt is for bringing קרבנות, Korbanos, not
for eating קרבנות. Korbanos.
So either it's forbidden to eat the שיירים? shirayim? You can't use
that salt.
They bought salt for the things that go up on the מזבח.
Mizbeiach.
Okay, we're talking about salt even before it was put on the
מזבח. Mizbeiach. But I think he was saying before there was a
pile of salt.
Right. It was a pile on the ramp or it was a
pile in a room. We're about to describe that. So don't use
that to eat your קרבן, Korban, says שמואל. Shmuel. But you can
use it to salt your קרבן. Korban. So Michael says, why can't
you eat... why can't you... you know, what's the חידוש chiddush to
say they can salt their קרבנות? Korbanos? You use it to salt
everybody's
קרבן. Korban. Exactly.
To let them borrow from public funds this salt. Right.
That's like, they borrow from the שקלים. Shekalim. So the גמרא Gemara
says like this, קא סלקא דעתך, ka salka daitach, we assumed, מאי
לקרבנן mai l'korbanan when שמואל Shmuel says that they use it for
their קרבן, Korban, what does that mean? למלוח קרבנן, limloach korbanan, to
salt their קרבן Korban to put it on the מזבח. Mizbeiach. And
לאכול le'echol when he says you can't use it for eating, it
means אכילת קדשים. achilas kodshim. You can't use it when they eat
the קרבנות Korbanos to put it on... to salt their meat. So
השתא למלוח עורות קדשים יהבינן, לאכילת קדשים לא יהבינן? Hashta limloach oros
kodshim yahavinan, l'achilas kodshim lo yahavinan? What... what are you talking about?
We give them salt to even salt their leather, you know, because
the salting would be a process of tanning it or, you know,
somehow processing it. We let them use the salt even to salt
the leather that comes from the animal. Certainly we should let them
use the salt to eat it. The eating is a מצוה Mitzvah
of the... of the קרבן. Korban. How do you know you let
them use this salt to tan their leather? דתניא, D'tanya, we taught
in a ברייתא. Beraisa. And here we finally see where the salt
was.
דבשלשה מקומות המלח נתונה. D'bishlosha mekomos hamelach nesuna. The salt is in
three places in the מקדש: Mikdash: בלשכת המלח, B'lishkas Hamelach, in the
chamber of salt. That would be the salt room that they would
have all the salt. Is that... I don't know, we'll have to
look at a diagram. ועל גבי הכבש, V'al gabei hakeves, on the
ramp. ובראש המזבח, U'v'rosh hamizbeiach, and at the top of the מזבח.
Mizbeiach. And they would all be used for different things. בלשכת המלח,
B'lishkas Hamelach, in the chamber of salt, ששם מולחין עורות קדשים, shesham
molchin oros kodshim, there you would use the salt from there—not necessarily
you do it in that room, but you would take the salt
from that room to be מולח moleach the skins, the leathers of
the קרבנות Korbanos so that they would be like, you know, whatever,
more pliable, more usable.
So that's from that room. ועל גבי הכבש, V'al gabei hakeves, on
the ramp, ששם מולחין את האיברים. shesham molchin es haeivarim. You would
use that salt and you would do the limbs of the קרבן,
Korban, like of an עולה, Olah, and of the inners. There you
would do all of the the meat that you would salt to
put on the מזבח. Mizbeiach. You would do that on the ramp.
ובראש המזבח, U'v'rosh hamizbeiach, and at the top of the
מזבח...
Mizbeiach... בלשכת המלח? B'lishkas Hamelach? Okay, I just want to show where
it is. All right. Down here, there, okay here.
Oh, that makes sense. It's right... it's right in the עזרה. Azarah.
Right... you know, right as soon as you get in the עזרה
Azarah because you need to... ready access to that. And it's also
sense that it's... right near the כבש, keves, right? Because you need
a sort of ready access to that for all the קרבנות. Korbanos.
Sorry, so where... right, all right. And where was it on the...
on the כבש? keves? Somewhere on here, somewhere in a middle point
of the כבש. keves. Now on one of these side ramps?
Maybe right before the side ramp because before they actually got to
then... I don't know. So anyway, that they would use for... more
salting their meat.
ובראש המזבח, U'v'rosh hamizbeiach, and at the top of the מזבח, Mizbeiach,
ששם מולחין הקומץ והלבונה. shesham molchin hakometz v'halevona.
So this would be... do the more non-meat products. The קומץ Kometz
and the לבונה Levona and the... there you go, yeah, Michael showed
him the picture. Michael, okay, there you go. The קומץ Kometz and
לבונה Levona והקטרת. v'haktoret. Now קטרת Ktoret is a little bizarre because
קטרת Ktoret is for the מזבח הזהב. Mizbeiach Hazahav. I'll get back
to that in a minute. ומנחת כהנים ומנחת כהן משיח, U'minchas kohanim
u'minchas kohen mashiach, and the מנחה Mincha of the כהנים Kohanim that
you would burn completely. ומנחת נסכים, U'minchas nesachim, and the מנחה Mincha
of the נסכים nesachim that you would burn completely that came with
the animal קרבן, Korban, ועולת העוף, v'olas ha-of, and you would do
one meat thing, the bird עולה. Olah. Now, it's a little bizarre.
What's the קטרת Ktoret doing on that list? Right? The קטרת Ktoret
you burn on the מזבח הזהב. Mizbeiach Hazahav. So presumably... and also
why are you separating the animal parts from the... from these sort
of more non-animal food, I mean, everything has to get burnt on
ראש המזבח. Rosh HaMizbeach. You have to take the limbs of the
קרבן Korban to the ראש Rosh wherever you do the זריקת הדם.
Zrikat HaDam. תוספות Tosafot basically says that it's to keep things clean
and not bloody. So for whatever reason, so if you're using animal
parts, there's a lot of blood in that area. So, although
presumably you're holding it and not putting it on the ground, but
whatever it is, you want to do salting of the non-bloody items
in a different space. So therefore even the קטורת Ketoret that you're
going to do on the מזבח הזהב, Mizbeach HaZahav,
you'll do it in the non-bloody space of salting, so you have
to go to the top of the מזבח, Mizbeach, salt it, come
all the way down and go into the מזבח הזהב, Mizbeach HaZahav,
which is a little crazy. But why not take the salt out
of the salt room? Why not make a separate pile of salt?
So I don't know, for whatever reason they had three piles and
there's one which they used for more of the כהנים's Kohanim personal
use for the leathers, one on the ramp they used for the
meat where it got bloody that area, and one at the top
where they used for the non-meat products.
And the reason why you're salting the קטורת Ketoret again was what?
I didn't understand that.
Because it's something that's burnt, and הכול—almost Ha-Kol everything that's burnt even
though it's an inner מזבח, Mizbeach, that was my focus. But this
is the opinion that you do.
דאמר שמואל, De-amar Shmuel, to the כהן Kohen they gave a leather,
the עורות. orot.
An עולה Olah and any קרבן Korban that they got the meat
and a חטאת and an אשם, Asham, any קרבן Korban that they
got all the meat from, they would get. Not a שלמים, Shlamim,
but basically an עולה, Olah, even though they don't get any meat,
they get the leather, and a חטאת and an אשם.
Asham. I'll give you a ramp, the stairs, so the blood can
run down.
Oh, there you go. Okay, so גמרא Gemara says anyway, the גמרא
Gemara says like this. So if they're obviously allowed to use salt
for their leather, they can use salt for their meat. So what
the heck is שמואל Shmuel saying? אלא, Ela, rather, מאי לקרבנם, Mai
l'korbanam, what when שמואל Shmuel says they can use their salt, what
does it mean? It doesn't mean for their salt to burn on
the—for their קרבנות Korbanot to burn on the מזבח. Mizbeach. It means
לאכילת קרבנם, L'achilat korbanam, to eat the meat of their קרבן. Korban.
And מאי לאכילה, Mai l'achila, what does he say you can't use
it for eating? It means אכילה דחולין. Achila d'Chulin. When you're eating,
you know, non-קרבנות, Korbanot, you cannot use the salt. גמרא Gemara says
אכילה דחולין פשיטא מאי בעא. Achila d'Chulin peshita mai ba-ei.
Obviously you can't use it for חולין. Chulin. What are you doing
bringing—bringing חולין Chulin in? Now רש"י Rashi says חולין בעזרה. Chulin ba-Azara.
חולין בעזרה Chulin ba-Azara is when you're bringing it as a קרבן.
Korban. But regardless, it's not appropriate to be bringing your, you know,
wrapped up sandwich with you into the בית המקדש.
Beit HaMikdash. I wouldn't eat a sandwich in the מקדש Mikdash with
all this barbeque. Right. So anyway the גמרא's Gemara saying פשיטא, Peshita,
of
course you're not using your salt for that, why does שמואל Shmuel
have to say it? And the list goes on and on with
this. So the גמרא Gemara says no, אף
על גב דאמר מר, Af al gav de-amar Mar, although we said
יאכלו, Yochlu, שיאכלו עם חולין ותרומה כדי שתהא נאכלת על השובע, She-yochlu
im Chulin u-Truma kedei she-tehei ne-echelet al ha-sova, that when you eat
the קרבן Korban you should, like the קרבן פסח Korban Pesach but
true by any קרבן, Korban, you should first get yourself pretty full
with other things so you don't eat the meat ravenously. You eat
it על השובע, al ha-sova, which is considered like you eat it
because you know, it's you know, in a more respectful way and
because of a delicacy and not because you're ravenous. So you have
to eat some חולין Chulin before you eat your קרבן. Korban. אפילו
הכי, Afilu hachi, and I might think therefore you can use it
to salt your חולין, Chulin, אפילו הכי מלח דקדשים לא יהבינן להו.
Afilu hachi melach de-Kodshim lo yahavinan le-hu. We do not give them
the salt which is intended for קרבן Korban use. So although this
is serving קרבן Korban purposes, it's not for קרבן Korban use. So
again what have we said? We said you give the כהנים Kohanim
their salt to use for—for some things, not other things. What are
the some things, not other things? So now we have translated שמואל
Shmuel to say, you give it to them to use to salt
their קרבן Korban meat for their—to salt their קרבן Korban meat—to eat
the meat of their—eat the meat of their קרבן, Korban, not to
put on the מזבח, Mizbeach, to eat it like they can use
for their leather. That they can because at least it's being used
for קדשים Kodshim even though for personal benefit of the כהן. Kohen.
But you can't use it on their חולין Chulin even though it's
serving a קדשים Kodshim purpose, it's not being placed on קדשים Kodshim
and therefore you cannot use it.
We'll continue tomorrow.